Hi. I'm going to ask you to raise your arms and wave back,
مرحباً. أريد أن أطلب منكم رفع أيديكم والتلويح بها الى الخلف
just the way I am -- kind of a royal wave.
مثلما أفعل-- بطريقة الموجة الملكية
You can mimic what you can see.
يمكنكم محاكاة ما تشاهدونه
You can program the hundreds of muscles in your arm.
يمكنكم برمجة مئات العضلات في يديكم
Soon, you'll be able to look inside your brain and program,
قريباً، ستتمكنوا من رؤية ما بداخل أدمغتكم وبرمجتها،
control the hundreds of brain areas that you see there.
التحكم في مئات المناطق للدماغ التي ترونها هناك
I'm going to tell you about that technology.
سأخبركم عن تلك التكنلوجيا
People have wanted to look inside the human mind,
أراد الناس رؤية ما بداخل العقل البشري
the human brain, for thousands of years.
الدماغ البشري، لآلاف السنين
Well, coming out of the research labs just now, for our generation, is the possibility to do that.
حسناً، خرج للتو من مختبرات البحث للتو إمكانية فعل ذلك
People envision this as being very difficult.
تصوّر الناس أنها في غاية الصعوبة
You had to take a spaceship, shrink it down, inject it into the bloodstream.
توجب عليك إتخاذ سفينة فضاء، تقلص حجمها، ثم ضخها الى الدورة الدموية
It was terribly dangerous. (Laughter)
كانت خطيرة للغاية
You could be attacked by white blood cells in the arteries.
قد يتم مهاجمتك من قبل خلايا الدم البيضاء في الشرايين
But now, we have a real technology to do this.
لكن الآن، لدينا تكنلوجيا حقيقية لفعل ذلك
We're going to fly into my colleague Peter's brain.
سنقوم بالتحليق داخل دماغ زميلي بيتر
We're going to do it non-invasively using MRI.
سنقوم بفعل ذلك بدون الإنتشار بإستخدام التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي
We don't have to inject anything. We don't need radiation.
لا يتوجب علينا حقن أي شئ. لا نحتاج لأشعة
We will be able to fly into the anatomy of Peter's brain -- literally, fly into his body --
سنتمكن من التحليق في تشريح دماغ بيتر-- حرفياً التحليق في جسمه--
but more importantly, we can look into his mind.
لكن الأهم من ذلك، يمكننا رؤية ما بداخل دماغه
When Peter moves his arm, that yellow spot you see there
عندما يحرك بيتر يده، تلك النقطة الصفراء التي ترونها هناك
is the interface to the functioning of Peter's mind taking place.
هي الواجهة لعمل عقل بيتر كما يعمل
Now you've seen before that with electrodes you can control robotic arms,
وها أنتم شاهدتموها مع القطب الكهربائي الذي يتحكم في يد الروبوت
that brain imaging and scanners can show you the insides of brains.
هذا التصوير الدماغي والماسحات يمكنها عرض ما بداخل الأدمغة
What's new is that that process has typically taken days or months of analysis.
الجديد هو أن هذه العملية كانت تستغرق أيام أو شهور من التحليل
We've collapsed that through technology to milliseconds,
لقد قلصنا ذلك عبر التكنلوجيا الى أجزاء من الثانية
and that allows us to let Peter to look at his brain in real time as he's inside the scanner.
التي تمكن بيتر من رؤية ما بداخل دماغة مباشرة طالما هو داخل الماسحة الضوئية
He can look at these 65,000 points of activation per second.
يمكنه رؤية 65000 نقطة للتفعيل في كل ثانية
If he can see this pattern in his own brain, he can learn how to control it.
اذا أستطاع رؤية الأنماط داخل دماغة، يمكنه تعلم كيفية التحكم فيها
There have been three ways to try to impact the brain:
كان هناك ثلاث طرق لمحاولة التأثير على المخ:
the therapist's couch, pills and the knife.
ملمس الأريكة، الحبوب المعالجة، وسكيناً
This is a fourth alternative that you are soon going to have.
هذا هو البديل الرابع الذي سيتوافر لكم قريباً
We all know that as we form thoughts, they form deep channels in our minds and in our brains.
جميعنا يعرف أنه عندما نشكّل الأفكار فأنها تصنع قنوات عميقة في أمخاخنا وأدمغتنا
Chronic pain is an example. If you burn yourself, you pull your hand away.
الألم المزمن على سبيل المثال. اذا أحرقت نفسك، فأنك تسحب يدك بعيداً
But if you're still in pain in six months' or six years' time,
لكن اذا كنت في ألم متواصل خلال فترة ستة أشهر أو ستة سنوات
it's because these circuits are producing pain that's no longer helping you.
هذا بسبب أن الدوائر التي تنتج الألم لم تعد تساعدك
If we can look at the activation in the brain that's producing the pain,
اذا نظرت في طريقة تفعيل الدماغ التي تنتج ذلك الألم
we can form 3D models and watch in real time the brain process information,
يمكنك تشكيل نموذج ثلاثي الأبعاد ومراقبة عملية معالجة الدماغ للمعلومات في زمن مباشر
and then we can select the areas that produce the pain.
وبعدها يمكنك إختيار المناطق التي تنتج الألم
So put your arms back up and flex your bicep.
اذا ضعوا أيديكم في الخلف ومرّن عضلتك
Now imagine that you will soon be able to look inside your brain
الآن تخيلوا أنكم قريباً سيمكنكم رؤية ما بداخل أدمغتكم
and select brain areas to do that same thing.
وأختر منطقة الدماغ التي تفعل الشئ نفسه
What you're seeing here is, we've selected the pathways in the brain of a chronic pain patient.
ما ترونه هنا هو، قمنا بإختيار مسارات الدماغ لمريض بالألم المزمن
This may shock you, but we're literally reading this person's brain in real time.
ربما يفجعكم هذا، لكنكم حرفياً تقرأون دماغ هذا الشخص في زمن مباشر
They're watching their own brain activation,
أنهم يشاهدون طريقة تفعيل أدمغتهم
and they're controlling the pathway that produces their pain.
ويقومون بالتحكم في المسارات التي تنتج الألم
They're learning to flex this system that releases their own endogenous opiates.
يتعلمون تمرين هذا النظام الذي يطلق المواد الأفيونية الخاصة بهم
As they do it, in the upper left is a display
وبينما يفعلون هذا، على الشمال في الأعلى يتم العرض
that's yoked to their brain activation of their own pain being controlled.
وهذا يرتبط بنشاطتهم الدماغي لآلامهم التي سيطروا عليها
When they control their brain, they can control their pain.
عندما يتحكمون في دماغهم، يتحكمون في آلالامهم
This is an investigational technology,
هذه تكنلوجيا تقوم بالتحقيق
but, in clinical trials, we're seeing a 44 to 64 percent decrease in chronic pain patients.
لكن في تجارب معملية نشهد تناقص 44 الى 64 في المائة في مرضى الألم المزمن
This is not "The Matrix." You can only do this to yourself. You take control.
ليس هذا "الماتركس". يمكنك فقط فعل هذا لنفسك. أنت تتحكم
I've seen inside my brain. You will too, soon.
لقد رايت ما بداخل دماغي. يمكنكم أيضاً، قريباً
When you do, what do you want to control?
عندما تستطيع، ما الذي تريد التحكم فيه؟
You will be able to look at all the aspects that make you yourself, all your experiences.
ستكون قادراً على النظر في كل الجوانب التي صنعت شخصيتك، كل خبراتك
These are some of the areas we're working on today that I don't have time to go into in detail.
هذه بعض المناطق التي نعمل عليها اليوم التي لا يسمح الزمن بالدخول في تفاصيلها
But I want to leave with you the big question.
لكني أريد ترككم مع السؤال الكبير
We are the first generation that's going to be able to enter into,
أنتم أول الأجيال التي ستكون قادرة على الإقتحام في هذا
using this technology, the human mind and brain.
بإستخدام هذه التكنلوجيا، عقل البشري والدماغ
Where will we take it?
أين سنتستخدمها؟